Guide to the Legal Records Relating to Sinclair Lewis
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Legal Records Relating to Sinclair Lewis
1919-1984
YCAL MSS 1104
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.0
10 boxes + 1 broadside
The Legal Records Relating to Sinclair Lewis consist of records maintained by Mellville H. Cane, Pincus Berner, Paul Gitlin, Eugene Winick and other attorneys affiated with the law firm of Ernst, Cane and Berner and its later iterations. In addition to correspondence between Lewis and his attorneys, the records include drafts and copies of Sinclair Lewis's will; correspondence and documents concerning his death and estate; records regarding his writings, including contracts and agreements, and permissions and rights inquiries handled by attorneys after Lewis's death.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Wills and Estate Records, 1919-1982. II. Records Relating to Sinclair Lewis's Writings, 1935-1984. III. May 2017 Addition Regarding the Estate of Sinclair Lewis, 1927-1968.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc. on the Sinclair Lewis Fund, 2015.
Scope and Contents
The Legal Records Relating to Sinclair Lewis consist of records maintained by Mellville H. Cane (executor of Lewis's estate), Pincus Berner, Paul Gitlin, Eugene Winick and other attorneys affiliated with the law firm of Ernst, Cane and Berner and its later iterations. In addition to correspondence between Lewis and his attorneys, the records include drafts and copies of Sinclair Lewis's will; correspondence and documents concerning his death and estate; records regarding his writings, including contracts and agreements, and permissions and rights inquiries handled by attorneys after Lewis's death. Also included is a photograph of Lewis and his wife, the journalist Dorothy Thompson (1893-1961), and photographs of an unidentified exhibition of Sinclair Lewis books and manuscripts. Additional records received in 2017 include legal and financial documents relating to the divorce of Sinclair Lewis and his first wife, Grace Hegger Lewis, and subsequent alimony issues, and correspondence relating to the publication of a biography of Lewis by Mark Schorer.
Authors, American -- 20th Century; Executors and administrators -- New York (State) -- New York; Lawyers -- New York (State) -- New York; Photographs; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Lawyers -- New York (State) -- New York -- 20th Century; Berner, Pincus; Cane, Melville, 1879-1980; Gitlin, Paul; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951; Schorer, Mark, 1908-1977; Thompson, Dorothy, 1893-1961; Winick, Eugene
- Wills and Estate Records, 1919–1982, undated; Series I; 1.5; 4 boxes + 1 broadside
  Arrangement
  Arranged in subseries based on file names and numbers assigned by attorneys.
  Scope and Contents
  Includes correspondence, drafts and copies of wills; documents relating to Lewis's death; records relating to Thorvale Farm, Lewis's home in Williamstown, Massachusetts; estate tax proceedings and probate papers; income tax records; photographs; a script of a stage play written by Henry S. Bloomgarden and Malcolm Wells about Lewis and his second wife Dorothy Thompson, and correspondence regarding the script.
  - Will of Sinclair Lewis (8510)
    - Melville H. Crane and Sinclair Lewis correspondence, 1944–1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Copies of wills and notes regarding changes, 1919-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
  - Williamstown, Massachusetts [Thorvale Farm] (8511)
    - Correspondence, 1946–1950 (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
      Includes correspondence between Sinclair Lewis, Melville H. Crane, and Sanborn G. Tenney.
    - Contracts and agreements, 1946–1951 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Plaza Art Galleries sale of estate, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Income tax returns, 1947–1949 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Thorvale Farm sales brochures, postcards and maps, 1948, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Thorvale Farm map and house plans (Box 8 (Broadside))
    - Thorvale Farm sale, 1951–1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Williamstown National Bank checkbook, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Estate Tax Proceedings and Probate Papers (9864)
    - Estate tax proceedings, 1928–1980 (Box 2, Folder 18-21)
    - Williamstown, Massachusetts property, 1944-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Probate papers, 1951–1964 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Plaza Art Galleries sale of estate, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Academy of Arts and Letters exhibition lists, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Ledger sheets, 1951–1956 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Income Tax and Statements (9863)
    - 1970, 1970–1971 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - 1971, 1971-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - 1972, 1972–1973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - 1973, 1973–1974 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - 1974, 1974–1975 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - 1975, 1975–1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - 1976, 1976–1977 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - 1977, 1977–1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - 1978, 1978–1979 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - 1980, 1980–1981 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - 1981 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - 1982 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Lewis IRS tax lien, 1954–1982 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Sinclair Lewis Estate ("Dorothy and Red" Play) (9323)
    - Correspondence, typescript photocopy of script, "Dorothy and Red" by Henry S. Bloomgarden and Malcolm Wells, 1964–1967 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous Files (no file numbers)
    - Grace Hegger Trust, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous Lewis estate papers, 1931-1949, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
      Includes photograph of Sinclair Lewis and Dorothy Thompson and unidentified photograph of an exhibition of Sinclair Lewis books and manuscripts.
    - Clippings, 1932, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Records Relating to Sinclair Lewis Writings, 1935-1984, undated; Series II; 1.3; 3 boxes
  Arranged by title of work and file number assigned by attorneys.
  Includes correspondence, contracts and agreements, and permissions and rights inquiries related to Sinclair Lewis's writings. The Man from Main Street was a collection of non-fiction articles by Sinclair Lewis edited by Melville H. Cane and Harry E. Maule, published by Random House in 1953.
  - Angela Is Twenty-Two (9862)
    - Correspondence, 1938–1947 (Box 5, Folder 46-51)
    - Contracts and agreements, 1938-1942, undated (Box 5, Folder 52-55)
  - Cass Timberlane (9869)
    - Correspondence and royalty report, 1945–1946 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Elmer Gantry motion picture (9859)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1982, undated (Box 6, Folder 57-59)
    - Contracts and agreements, 1954–1959 (Box 6, Folder 60-63)
  - The Man from Main Street (9324)
    - Correspondence, 1952–1963 (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Melville H. Crane editorial notes, lists, and introduction to volume, 1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - "Notices, etc.", 1953 (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - "Pieces agreed upon," sample dust jacket, and photostatic copy of "Self-Conscious America" by Sinclair Lewis from the American Mercury, October, 1925, undated (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Miscellaneous Writings, 1935-1947, undated (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Permissions and Rights Inquiries (9871)
    - Arrowsmith, 1966–1981 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Babbitt, 1964-1981, undated (Box 7, Folder 70-73)
    - Cass Timberlane, 1968–1981 (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Dodsworth, 1973–1983 (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - Elmer Gantry, 1968–1982 (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - Go East, Young Man, 1967–1971 (Box 7, Folder 77)
    - Miscellaneous writings, 1968-1984, undated (Box 7, Folder 78-80)
- May 2017 Addition Regarding the Estate of Sinclair Lewis, 1927-1968; Series III; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Includes correspondence, legal and financial records relating to the divorce of Sinclair Lewis and Grace Hegger Lewis; the biography of Sinclair Lewis by Mark Schorer; and financial records relating to bank accounts and securities.
  - "Grace H. Lewis v. S. Lewis (papers only)" (5691)
    Includes legal and financial documents relating to the divorce of Sinclair Lewis and Grace Hegger Lewis, and subsequent alimony issues
    - Legal documents, 1927–1932 (Box 9, Folder 81-86)
    - Notes, financial documents, and clippings, 1927–1930 (Box 9, Folder 87-88)
  - "Re: Mark Schorer" (9322)
    Includes correspondence between McGraw-Hill Book Company, Inc., attorneys Melville Cane and Pincus Berner, and author Mark Schorer, and other material relating to the writing and publication of Schorer's biography, Sinclair Lewis, an American Life (New York: McGraw-Hill, c1961)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1957, undated (Box 10, Folder 89-92)
    - "Sinclair Lewis at Home: 1942" by Mark Schorer, undated (Box 10, Folder 93)
    - Correspondence regarding Esquire magazine article, 1958 (Box 10, Folder 94)
    - Legal agreements, 1952 (Box 10, Folder 95)
    - Reprints and clippings, 1945–1966 (Box 10, Folder 96)
    - Royalty statements, 1961–1966 (Box 10, Folder 97)
    - Yale University Library, undated (Box 10, Folder 98)
    - Requests for permission to publish photographs from Schorer biography, 1972–1980 (Box 10, Folder 99)
    - Correspondence between Edward C. Aswell and Sinclair Lewis, 1938 October (Box 10, Folder 100)
      Typed copies of letters from Lewis to Edward C. Aswell regarding book recommendations
  - "Income and Securities" (9328)
    - Bank statements and cancelled checks, 1950–1956 (Box 10, Folder 101-106)
    - Bank statements and cancelled checks, 1956–1961 (Box 11, Folder 107-108)
    - Dividend and interest reports and securities and credit advises, 1951–1961 (Box 11, Folder 109-113)
      Includes Guaranty Trust Company of New York deposit passbook (1951-1960)
    - Michael Lewis trust, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 114)
    - Curtis Brown, Ltd., 1952 (Box 11, Folder 115)
      Cover letter and television script adaptation of Sinclair Lewis's World So Wide by Arnold Schulman
  - "Miscellaneous Papers and Newspaper Clippings" (9857)
    - Miscellaneous notes, legal and financial dcouments, and newspaper and magazine clippings concerning Sinclair Lewis, 1922-1929, undated (Box 11, Folder 116-120)